So now that you have this new knowledge,
the exercise now is to continue on
your component exploration journey and now you
have basically the opportunity to
architect your components however you see fit.
Do you want to go ahead and just have
these display components that receive data from the parent,
and then if it makes changes,
emit that upwards or do you
want to just keep everything at the top?
Like you can figure out how you want to
play around with that and see what works well for you.
All right, and we're back.
So one of the questions that came up during
the exercise is like people were playing around,
and what they notice is,
is that if you mutate the prop,
everything does seem to work.
So in other words, if you're in here for example,
and we said this dot user dot name equals,
let's do Dominique.
Again, it will technically work.
The principle I want to stress here,
it's not so much that a question of whether or not it works or not,
but more so that when it comes to best practices for architecting apps,
you want to keep it as easy as possible to debug what's wrong.
This is why I'm also a big fan of when you have error reporting,
or for example, we'll talk about styling later,
but when we go too far in terms of our optimizations of like,
well, it's easier to just do this,
it can make it tricky to track where things are happening.
So when it comes to UI,
a lot of it ends up going down to where's your source of truth.
When you allow your code base to start
messing with that source of truth in different places,
all of a sudden it becomes a lot trickier to
figure out why and when something happened.
Whereas if you follow this pattern of
emitting for children to parent,
you'll always know that if in the future the user has
a bug where this list, for example, is broken,
you'll know that basically you probably should be looking at
the parent and basically you'll probably be able to solve it just off that alone.
But if you allow the mutation of props elsewhere,
all of a sudden that guarantee becomes
far less likely is because you just don't know what's happening.
So I always err on the side of keeping it easy when it comes
to maintenance and debugging.
So let's take a look at this exercise, shall we?
Okay. That's not what I wanted at all.
Okay, perfect. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to open up
my ATLA forum.
Actually, let me just, good.
So ATLA forum, great.
Fresh, cool. Okay.
So a good component to illustrate this is going to be the favoriting button.
Because we can see here that inside of
App.View we're actually managing our favorite lists here at the very top.
So let's go ahead and create that favorite list component.
So favorite list, great.
Actually, you know what? I think favorite characters is actually a bit more accurate.
Favorite characters, great.
And then I realized though, actually, wait, I misspoke.
Rather than the favorite characters,
we actually want to create individual character cards.
That's what we want.
So let me rename this now to character card.
And so what we have here now, what I did earlier in case when people see that,
this is just a VS code extension.
So, or not an extension, it's one of the short hands.
So it's a short code that I customized so that when I type
sfc for a single file component,
it would automatically spit out my building blocks for me.
Okay. So what we have here is we have this html that we basically want to refactor.
Which is what we're looping through right here.
Okay. So I'm going to go ahead and actually just copy this as a,
should I do it as a list item?
Let's just do it as a div.
Actually, this would be cleaner so that it doesn't have to be in the list.
So we'll have a div, and the div will contain all this stuff.
Now, we need to move some functionality over though.
So here's our placeholder.
We need to move the favorite character functionality.
Okay. And I think we need a prop,
because we need to actually know what character we're rendering.
So the character, this case, again, would be a type object.
And so I'm not going to actually break down the individual properties.
And then that way we can get character.name.
And then for now, let's not worry about this function because this will break.
And then that's it.
Okay. So to prove that this works, we're going to go ahead and
import our character card.
And then drop that here.
And then we're going to use it inside of our placeholder.
And we'll pass in the character as a prop.
So this is reusing all the stuff that we did earlier.
Okay. Everything is appearing as expected.
Now, the difference here, though, is that this favorite character functionality
doesn't work because, guess what, this card does not care about.
Like, its responsibility is not to track the favorite list.
So to the point of what I was talking about earlier,
you can theoretically pass favorite list as a prop to this component.
And then you could have theoretically the component update favorite list.
But again, that starts to convolute the scope of the data and how it's being owned.
That's not its goal.
Its goal is to say, hey, I'm going to show a card of my characters.
And by the way, when someone clicks the favorite event, I will go ahead and
tell the parent of whatever contacts I'm in that the user decided they wanted to
favorite this card.
Whatever you do with that, that's up to you.
So what we've got to do here is we'll define our emits call.
And we'll just call it, we'll keep it simple, actually,
because emits our scope to the specific component.
We'll just call it a favorite event.
That's just what's happening.
So now that we have the favorite event, we can say, okay, well,
when this happens, this dot emit.
This dot emit, what event are we emitting?
It's called favorite.
But more importantly, actually, what we can do is we can actually
pass in an argument to our emitted function, which is this dot character.
So we can save that.
And then this time now, we can click, favorite character, okay, great.
Now that we have this, we can come over here and then we can say, ah, yes.
So on the character card, we have this favorite event that's going to happen.
And when it does, we can say add, let's see, add favorite character.
And so if we take a look now, let's update this method.
It's called add favorite character.
And what you end up getting, because you're passing it as an argument,
is a payload.
Basically, you can rename it, whatever you want.
But generally speaking, we call it a payload because this is coming from the event.
So again, the way this is connected to show this side by side.
This dot emit emits this as the event name.
And this here, the second argument, will basically be the payload.
So it's generally frowned upon, for example, to just keep adding to this.
If you're like, oh, I want to add a custom ID, like 123, you wouldn't do this.
You would actually instead just pass a single object.
That's like, this is the character and this is the ID.
So payloads are typically done in a single argument.
Try not to spread them out beyond that.
And like I said, if you need more nesting, then by all means use an object.
But we don't need to do that.
So let's go ahead and actually just emit the character directly.
And then with that payload, we can actually just push that over.
So let's go ahead and verify that this works.
Refresh, boom, anezuko, and bam.
And there you have it.
That is a way that you can implement the props in a way that lets you render
exactly what you need.
But then when it's time to actually do something, the child can tell the parent
that, hey, there's this thing that I'm requesting, please do what you will with it.
Does anyone have any questions regarding what the solution that we just went over?
If you wanted to have your favorite, be a separate,
like a favorite module, and so if you want to call that a function in another
module, a child module, from the template code there or something.
So let me make sure I understand the question correctly.
So let's say in the event you're mentioning that the favorite functionality
is something that's shared amongst different UI components.
How would we share that amongst the different components?
Yeah, or I mean specifically you have a button with an ad click.
This is favorite character.
And let's say that function is actually in a different module.
Okay, so with this button you're saying that this is in a different module.
Yeah.
So okay, so you're saying that in this example you'd have like,
let's say we'd have a utilities folder that has a favorite.js, for example.
And so you're kind of referring to where there's like a function that like will.
Like I was thinking of a component that displays the favorites and
then have ad favorite function also inside there.
I see, okay, got it.
So the scope here is you're saying that having the favorite list scoped with
the component directly, so actually, so not this scenario.
The idea here actually being that instead,
let's go and create that favorite list, characters, dot view.
And so in this case, are you referring to the fact that like,
we would be rendering out the list here then?
Yeah.
So got it, so here, okay.
So inside of here, we're doing another refactoring here.
We have our data being the actual favorite list that's being tracked here.
And then this is where we're actually rendering the favorite list,
which is going to be this block right here.
And apparently we have an vls condition, so that is that whole thing.
And then drop that in here.
Okay, so that should be good.
Favorite list is good.
That's good, okay.
Now, the question here is we need to import favorite characters.
So let's do that real quick, favorite characters, and drop that as well.
And then once we have that, you said that you want to render it here.
Favorite characters, like this.
Okay.
And I guess you tell me where you'd put the function to add favorites, but
the variable is inside that module.
Correct.
So how would you go about it?
Okay, and then variables in here.
And I think something's missing, though, it must be delta resolve component.
Because I think I misspelled it.
What'd you say?
Favorite characters.
See, the one off, the S gets me.
This is why I generally do list, anyhow.
Okay, no favorite characters yet.
Okay, so are you saying that in this particular context,
you're saying we clearly have the favorite functionality inside of the card here.
And you're saying that what if we had another section that also had a favorite
button to add characters?
I guess I'm just, just as is.
Yep.
How would you get the data over into the favorite list variable,
which is inside the favorite characters component?
Yeah, this is where it gets tricky.
So at least with the tools that we have now,
you would basically have to do, okay, so you've omitted this.
You would omit this.
I'm not sure it would actually make sense, because so
the thing about we have to remember when it comes to omits and props is that it's
a top down relationship.
And the problem we're trying to solve here is a sibling relationship,
because character card contains data that Benner statistics,
or no, not Benner statistics.
Favorite characters and character card are trying to talk to each other basically
at this point.
And so usually what happens at that point is where you want some sort of
alternative state management solution where you have like basically as a preview
is you would have stores and we probably would have like a favorite store.
And the favorite store becomes a file that becomes basically a JavaScript module
that's shared between the two components that care about that.
And that way the updating becomes cleaner.
And in fact, what's kind of interesting though is that once you start doing these
stores, sometimes the omit goes away actually, because now you're actually not
thinking about emitting to a parent, you're just updating the store.
And so that can do a lot in terms of like cleaning up code and that kind of stuff.
But I wanted to at least start with the fundamentals of like if you're
dealing with two components, parent child, this is like kind of like best practice
for how we approach things.
But then with tomorrow, once we talk about store module and
that kind of stuff, it's going to be all sorts of fun, so.
The situation you have here, this is where that generic list component could be useful.
Yep.
Where you're passing as a prop the list of characters into one list,
the list of favorites into the others.
And then using functions to update those separate lists.
Exactly.
Yep. Great.